Okay, so let's calculate float now.
Now what we have done so far, right,
we have basically followed my five steps.
So we are on the fifth step now.
Right, so we calculated the critical path.
Step number one.
Step number two was to note that float on
critical path is zero.
Step number three
was calculating the early
start and early finish, the forward pass.
and then step number four was calculating
the late finish and late start,
which is a backward pass.
So now my step number five is to calculate
the float on the
non-critical path activities.
Now technically though, we've already done
that.
I mean, let's think about this.
If you look at B, B can start on day two
or it could start on day five,
no impact on the schedule.
So in other words, it could start on day
two or be delayed.
by another three days and start on day
five, no impact on the schedule.
There's our float.
B has a float of three.
B has a float of three days.
Now, the way to calculate float,
though, the actual official formula for
like for calculating float is late finish
minus early finish.
Or late start minus early start.
You get the same answer, right?
So late finish minus the early finish.
Late start minus the early start.
Bottom, minus the top.
So if you look at B then, nine minus six
or five.
minus 2.
So B has a float of 3.
If you look at C, exactly the same thing.
It's either 16 minus 13 or 9 minus 6.
So C also has a float of 3, right?
Or understand.
What does the float mean?
C can start on day 6 or it could start on
day 9.
C can start on day 6
or it could be delayed
by another three days and start on day 9.
There's our float.
same with f 16 minus 15 or 10 minus 9 f
had the flow of 1 and then g 9 minus 8 or
3 minus 2 g also has the flow of 1 and
just as a check imbalance right or you
know just to verify for the critical path
right we said critical path flow is 0
let's just check that 0 minus 0 2 minus 2
flow is 0 with d 7 minus 7 2 minus 2 flow
is 0 you know 4 all of them, age,
16 minus 16, 9 minus 9, float is zero.
So there's your calculation of float.
Now notice something else down here
in this box is called total float, right?
I've got this term called total float.
Let's talk about this because there are
three types of float, right, which we are
going to cover in a separate video,
but I just want to mention this float here
because I've been talking about the float
for each of these activities.
That float is known as the total float.
So B has a total float of three.
C has a total float of three.
F has a total flow of one and G has a
total flow of one.
So that's what total,
so the floats I've been
talking about, they refer to total floats.
However, I need to expand on that because
there's something very important you need
to understand when it the floats or when
it comes to total float.
B has a total float of three.
C has a total flow of three.
B can be delayed by up to three days,
no impact on the schedule.
C can be delayed by up to three days,
However, since B and C are on the same
path, they're right next to each other,
on the same path, they share this float.
Right, so it's not like B can be delayed
by three days and C delayed by three days.
No.
In total, in total, You know, both B and C
can be delayed by up to three days.
If B is delayed by one day, now C can only
be delayed by two days.
If B gets delayed by two days,
now C can only be delayed by one day.
So that is what total float refers to.
Let's look at this logically.
B finishes on day six.
C starts on day six.
Now, if B gets delayed by one day,
B will finish on day seven.
And so C will start on day seven.
So 9 minus 7 is 2.
If B gets delayed by two days,
now B will start on day 8, or rather,
B will finish on day 8, C will start on
day 8.
So 9 minus 8 is 1.
So they share this float.
So a lot of times they might ask you what
is a total float of a path, right?
So, for example, what is the total float
of path A, B, C, I?
Total float of a path is wherever is the
highest float, highest total float.
So you never, never, never add float
values together, right?
B has a total float of three, C has a
total float of three.
If they asked you what is a total float of
A, B, C, I, the answer would be three.
In this case, they're both the same float.
If they were different, it'd be whatever
is the highest float.
So if you look at F here, A, B, F, I, F
has a float of one, B has a float of three.
If they ever ask you what is a total float
of A, B, F, FI, the answer would be three.
Whatever is the highest float.
Let's always remember that, never add
float values together.
If they're asking about total float,
what is a total float of a path?
You always take whatever is the highest
total float of the activities on that path.